{
  "title": "Computer_Organization - Computer_Organization — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Computer_Organization — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>An application executes \\(6.4 \\times 10^8\\) number of instructions in 6.3 seconds. There are four types of instructions, the details of which are given in the table. The duration of a clock cycle in nanoseconds is _________. (rounded off to one decimal place)\\( \\begin{array}{|c|c|c|}\n\\hline\n\\text{Instruction type} &amp; \\text{Clock cycles required per instruction (CPI)} &amp; \\text{Number of instructions executed} \\\\\n\\hline\n\\text{Branch} &amp; 2 &amp; 2.25 \\times 10^8 \\\\\n\\text{Load} &amp; 5 &amp; 1.20 \\times 10^8 \\\\\n\\text{Store} &amp; 4 &amp; 1.65 \\times 10^8 \\\\\n\\text{Arithmetic} &amp; 3 &amp; 1.30 \\times 10^8 \\\\\n\\hline\n\\end{array} \\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "3",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460842/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-51#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>A 5-stage instruction pipeline has stage delays of 180, 250, 150, 170, and 250, respectively, in nanoseconds. The delay of an inter-stage latch is 10 nanoseconds. Assume that there are no pipeline stalls due to branches and other hazards. The time taken to process 1000 instructions in microseconds is __________ . (rounded off to two decimal places) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "260.2",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460847/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-46#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Given a computing system with two levels of cache (L1 and L2) and a main memory. The first level (L1) cache access time is 1 nanosecond (ns) and the \"hit rate\" for L1 cache is 90% while the processor is accessing the data from L1 cache. Whereas, for the second level (L2) cache, the \"hit rate\" is 80% and the \"miss penalty\" for transferring data from L2 cache to L1 cache is 10 ns. The \"miss penalty\" for the data to be transferred from main memory to L2 cache is 100 ns. <br><br>Then the average memory access time in this system in nanoseconds is ___________ . (rounded off to one decimal place) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "4",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460848/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-45#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>For a direct-mapped cache, 4 bits are used for the tag field and 12 bits are used to index into a cache block. The size of each cache block is one byte. Assume that there is no other information stored for each cache block.  <br>\nWhich ONE of the following is the CORRECT option for the sizes of the main memory and the cache memory in this system (byte addressable), respectively? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>64 KB and 4 KB</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>128 KB and 16 KB</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>64 KB and 8 KB</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>128 KB and 6 KB</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>64 KB and 4 KB</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460806/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-29#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following is/are part of an Instruction Set Architecture of a processor? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The size of the cache memory</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The clock frequency of the processor</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The number of cache memory levels</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The total number of registers</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>The total number of registers</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460817/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-18#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>A computer has a memory hierarchy consisting of two-level cache (L1 and L2) and a main memory. If the processor needs to access data from memory, it first looks into L1 cache. If the data is not found in L1 cache, it goes to L2 cache. If it fails to get the data from L2 cache, it goes to main memory, where the data is definitely available. Hit rates and access times of various memory units are shown in the figure. The average memory access time in nanoseconds (ns) is _________. (rounded off to two decimal places) <br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Computer_Organization\\q43_7d1f00ff.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "11.83",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460037/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-43#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>A processor has 64 general-purpose registers and 50 distinct instruction types. An instruction is encoded in 32-bits. What is the maximum number of bits that can be used to store the immediate operand for the given instruction?\n<br><br>\nADD  R1, #25       // R1 = R1 + 25 <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>16</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>20</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>22</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>24</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>20</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460053/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-27#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Consider a memory system with 1M bytes of main memory and 16K bytes of cache memory. Assume that the processor generates 20-bit memory address, and the cache block size is 16 bytes. If the cache uses direct mapping, how many bits will be required to store all the tag values? [Assume memory is byte addressable, 1K = \\(2^{10}\\), 1M = \\(2^{20}\\).] <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(6 \\times 2^{10}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(8 \\times 2^{10}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{12}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2^{14}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(6 \\times 2^{10}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460054/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>A partial data path of a processor is given in the figure, where \\(RA\\), \\(RB\\), and \\(RZ\\) are 32-bit registers. Which option(s) is/are CORRECT related to arithmetic operations using the data path as shown? <br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Computer_Organization\\q17_85b8e89d.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The data path can implement arithmetic operations involving two registers.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The data path can implement arithmetic operations involving one register and one immediate value.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The data path can implement arithmetic operations involving two immediate values.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The data path can only implement arithmetic operations involving one register and one immediate value.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The data path can implement arithmetic operations involving two registers.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The data path can implement arithmetic operations involving one register and one immediate value.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The data path can implement arithmetic operations involving two immediate values.</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460063/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-17#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Suppose a program is running on a non-pipelined single processor computer system. The computer is connected to an external device that can interrupt the processor asynchronously. The processor needs to execute the interrupt service routine (ISR) to serve this interrupt. The following steps (not necessarily in order) are taken by the processor when the interrupt arrives:\n<br><br>\n(i) The processor saves the content of the program counter.\n<br>(ii) The program counter is loaded with the start address of the ISR.\n<br>(iii) The processor finishes the present instruction.\n<br><br>\nWhich ONE of the following is the CORRECT sequence of steps? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(iii), (i), (ii)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(i), (iii), (ii)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(i), (ii), (iii)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(iii), (ii), (i)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>(iii), (i), (ii)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460080/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>A processor uses a 32-bit instruction format and supports byte-addressable memory\naccess. The ISA of the processor has 150 distinct instructions. The instructions are\nequally divided into two types, namely R-type and I-type, whose formats are shown\nbelow.\n<br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Computer_Organization\\q51_81cf05b3.webp\"><br>\nIn the OPCODE, 1 bit is used to distinguish between I-type and R-type instructions\nand the remaining bits indicate the operation. The processor has 50 architectural\nregisters, and all register fields in the instructions are of equal size.<br>\nLet X be the number of bits used to encode the UNUSED field, Y be the number\nof bits used to encode the OPCODE field, and Z be the number of bits used to\nencode the immediate value/address field. The value of X + 2Y + Z is ______ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "34",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422846/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-51#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>A non-pipelined instruction execution unit operating at 2 GHz takes an average of\n6 cycles to execute an instruction of a program P. The unit is then redesigned to\noperate on a 5-stage pipeline at 2 GHz. Assume that the ideal throughput of the\npipelined unit is 1 instruction per cycle. In the execution of program P,\n20% instructions incur an average of 2 cycles stall due to data hazards and\n20% instructions incur an average of 3 cycles stall due to control hazards. The\nspeedup (rounded off to one decimal place) obtained by the pipelined design over\nthe non-pipelined design is ________ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "2.9",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422849/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-48#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>A processor with 16 general purpose registers uses a 32-bit instruction format. The\ninstruction format consists of an opcode field, an addressing mode field, two register\noperand fields, and a 16-bit scalar field. If 8 addressing modes are to be supported,\nthe maximum number of unique opcodes possible for every addressing mode\nis _________ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "32",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422850/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Consider a disk with the following specifications: rotation speed of 6000 RPM,\naverage seek time of 5 milliseconds, 500 sectors/track, 512-byte sectors.\nA file has content stored in 3000 sectors located randomly on the disk. Assuming\naverage rotational latency, the total time (in seconds, rounded off to 2 decimal\nplaces) to read the entire file from the disk is _______ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "29.5",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422854/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-43#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>An instruction format has the following structure:<br><br>\nInstruction Number: \\(Opcode \\; \\; destination reg, \\;\\; source reg-1, \\;\\;source reg-2\\)<br><br>\nConsider the following sequence of instructions to be executed in a pipelined\nprocessor:<br><br>\nI1: DIV R3, R1, R2 <br>\nI2: SUB R5, R3, R4 <br>\nI3: ADD R3, R5, R6 <br>\nI4: MUL R7, R3, R8 <br><br>\nWhich of the following statements is/are TRUE <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>There is a RAW dependency on R3 between I1 and I2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>There is a WAR dependency on R3 between I1 and I3</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>There is a RAW dependency on R3 between I2 and I3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>There is a WAW dependency on R3 between I3 and I4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>There is a RAW dependency on R3 between I1 and I2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422876/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-21#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}